Erwin Panofsky
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Correspondence, 1921-1978, undated, Series 1:; (Boxes 1-16; 16 linear ft. Reels 2108-2128)
  - Organizations, Societies, and Congresses, 1937-1967, 1.6:
    - John Hay Whitney Foundation - YMHA, New York, 1950-1960 (Box 16, Reel 2127)
      - John Hay Whitney Foundation (Box 16, Reel 2127)
      - YMHA, New York (Box 16, Reel 2127)
  - Periodicals, 1937-1967, 1.7:
    - America Illustrated - American Scholar, 1959-1965 (Box 16, Reel 2127)
      - Art Illustrated (Box 16, Reel 2127)
      - American Scholar (Box 16, Reel 2127)
    - Art Bulletin - Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists, 1952-1967 (Box 16, Reel 2127)
      - Art Bulletin, 1938-1967 (Box 16, Reel 2127)
      - Art Digest, 1953 (Box 16, Reel 2127)
      - Art in America, 1955-1965 (Box 16, Reel 2127)
      - Art News, 1957-1961 (Box 16, Reel 2127)
      - Art Quarterly, 1952 (Box 16, Reel 2127)
      - L'Arte, 1965-1966 (Box 16, Reel 2127)
      - Arte Antica e Moderna, 1961 (Box 16, Reel 2127)
      - Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists, 1958 (Box 16, Reel 2127)
    - Burlington Magazine - Diogène, 1937-1961 (Box 16, Reel 2127)
      - Burlington Magazine (Box 16, Reel 2127)
      - College Art Journal (Box 16, Reel 2127)
      - Cinnaissance des Arts (Box 16, Reel 2127)
      - Daedalus (Box 16, Reel 2127)
      - Diogène (Box 16, Reel 2127)
    - Gazette des Beaux-Arts (see also: Adhémar, Jean), 1948-1966 (Box 16, Reel 2127)
    - Isis, 1955-1960 (Box 16, Reel 2127)
    - Journal of Aesthetics and Art Criticism - Pageant, 1939-1963 (Box 16, Reel 2127)
      - Journal of Aesthetics and Art Criticism (Box 16, Reel 2127)
      - Journal of the Warburg and Courtauld Institutes (Box 16, Reel 2127)
      - Library Chronicle (Box 16, Reel 2127)
      - Magazine of Art (Box 16, Reel 2127)
      - Marsyas (Box 16, Reel 2127)
      - Master Drawings (Box 16, Reel 2127)
      - New York Times Book Review (Box 16, Reel 2127)
      - Pageant (Box 16, Reel 2127)
    - Phoebus - University Magazine, 1946-1964 (Box 16, Reel 2127)
      - Phoebus (Box 16, Reel 2127)
      - Phoenix (Box 16, Reel 2127)
      - Progress of Medieval and Renaissance Studies (Box 16, Reel 2127)
      - Revista de Occidente (Box 16, Reel 2127)
      - University Magazine (Princeton) (Box 16, Reel 2127)
  - Miscellaneous, 1940-1969, 1.8:
    - Acknowledgements, Early Netherlandish Painting, 1954 (Box 16, Reel 2127)
    - Book Dealers, Antiquarians, etc., 1949-1954 (Box 16, Reel 2127)
    - Homage Issue of Bulletin des Musée Royaux - Thank You Letters, 1955 (Box 16, Reel 2127)
    - Embassies and Consulates, 1961-1968 (Box 16, Reel 2127)
    - Festchrift Acknowledgements, 1961 (Box 16, Reel 2127)
    - H. P. Kraus Old and Rare Books, Manuscripts, Maps, 1955-1965 (Box 16, Reel 2127)
    - Photo Resources, 1951-1967 (Box 16, Reel 2127)
    - Seventieth Birthday, 1962 (Box 16, Reel 2127)
    - U. S. Government, 1954-1966 (Box 16, Reel 2127-2128)
    - Review Requests (various publishers), 1949-1968, (2 folders) (Box 16, Reel 2127-2128)
    - Requests for Contributions to Encyclopedias, Dictionaries, and Lexicons, 1940-1969 (Box 16, Reel 2127-2128)
    - Requests to Write Books, 1953-1962 (Box 16, Reel 2127-2128)
  - Unfilmed Correspondence, 1925-1967, undated, 1.9:
    - Correspondence, 1925-1967, undated, (4 folders) (Box 16, Reel unfilmed)
- Writings, 1915-1968, undated, Series 2:; (Boxes 17-19; 2.3 linear ft.)
  Writings by Panofsky consist of drafts, notes, and manuscripts of articles, book reviews, books, and lectures. The early writings are in German.
  This series is arranged by format.
  - Articles (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
    - "Artist, Scientist, Genius," (The Renaissance: Six Essays, Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1952) (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
      - Drafts and Notes, undated (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
      - Revised Version, 1962 (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
    - "Canopus Deus," (Gazette des Beaux Arts, LVI, 1961), undated (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
    - "Comments on Art and Reformation," (American Historical Association, 1960; Symbols of Transformation, The Art Museum, Princeton University, 1968 (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
    - "Dürer's Last Picture," (Burlington Magazine, March 1943), undated (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
    - "Erasmus and the Visual Arts" (Journal of the Warburg and Courtauld Institutes, XXXII, 1969) (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
      - Drafts, undated, (2 folders) (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
      - Manuscript, undated (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
      - Notes, undated (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
    - "The First Page of Vasari's 'Libro': A Study on the Gothic Style in the Judgment of the Italian Renaissance," undated (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
    - "Frank Aydelotte as Director of the Institute for advanced Study," [obituary] (Swarthmore College Bulletin, LIV, 5, 1957), circa 1956-1957 (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
    - "Giotto and Maimonides in Avignon," (Journal of the Walters Art Gallery, IV, 1941), undated (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
    - "Good Government or Fortune?: The Iconography of a Newly-Discovered Composition by Rubens," (Gazette des Beaux Arts, LXVIII, 1966; lecture version, Harvard and Stockholm, 1966), undated (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
    - "John Hey's Ecce Homo: Some Speculations about Its Author, Its Donor, and Its Iconography" (Brussels, Musée Royal des Beaux-Arts, Bulletin, v, 1956, pp. 95-132) (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
      - Corrected Draft, undated (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
      - Manuscript, undated (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
      - Research Notes and Correspondence, 1955-1956, undated (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
    - "The Ideological Antecedents of the Rolls-Royce Radiator," (Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society, CVII, 1963), circa 1962 (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
    - "In Defense of the Ivory Tower," (Association of Princeton Graduate Alumni, 1953; and revised version presented at 1957 Commencement), circa 1953 and 1957 (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
    - "The Mouse that Michelangelo Failed to Carve (Marsyas. Studies in the History of Art, Supplement 1, Essays in Memory of Karl Lehmann, New York, 1964), undated (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
    - "Nebulae in Pariete: Notes on Erasmus Eulogy on Dürer," (Journal of the Warurg Institute, 1951), undated (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
    - "On Movies" (Princeton University, Department of Art and Archaeology Bulletin, 1939; Rutgers College, 1946; Critique, 1947), circa 1934 (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
    - "Paul Coremans, The Promoter of a New Co-operation between the Natural Sciences and the History of Art," (Bulletin de l'Institut royal du patrimonie artistique, VIII, 1965, pp. 62-67), undated (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
    - "Postlogium Sugerianum," Art Bulletin, XXIX, 1947, p. 119), undated (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
    - Preface to M. J. Friedländer's Early Netherlandish Painting (1967 edition), circa 1967 "Das Problem des Stils in der Bildenden Kunst," 1915 (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
    - "Reintegration of a Book of Hours executed in the workshop of the Maître des Grandes Heures de Rohan,'" (Medieval Studies in the memory of A. Kingsley Porter, 1959), undated (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
    - "Rembrandt und das Judentum," (Jahrbuch der Hamburger Kunstsammlungen, XXVIII, 1974), 1920 (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
    - "Sokrates in Hamburg oder von Schönen und Guten," (Der Querschnitt, XI, no. 9, 1931, pp. 593-599; Gesellschaft5 der Bücherfreunde, 1962), 1951 (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
    - "Sol Aequinoctialis Fuit Creatus: Notes on a Composition by Lelio Orsi and Its Possible Connection with the Gregorian Calendar Reform," undated (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
    - "The Tomby at Arcady at the Fin-de-Siécle," (Wallraf-Richartz Jahrbuch, XXX, 1968), undated (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
    - "An Unpublished Portrait Drawing by Albrecht Dürer," (Master Drawings I, 1963), undated (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
    - Book Review, Goldschmidt, Adolph. Die Skulpturen von Freiburg aund Wechselburg, 1924-1925 (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
    - Books (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
      - The Iconography of Correggio's Camera di San Paolo (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
        - Drafts, undated, (3 folders) (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
        - Footnotes, undated (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
        - Galley Proofs (corrected), 1960 (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
        - Illustrations, undated (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
        - Manuscript, undated (Box 18, Reel unfilmed)
        - Manuscript (Italian Translation), undated (Box 18, Reel unfilmed)
      - Idea: The History of a Concept (Box 18, Reel unfilmed)
        - Appendices, undated (Box 18, Reel unfilmed)
        - Footnotes, undated (Box 18, Reel unfilmed)
        - Manuscript (1968 edition), circa 1967 (Box 18, Reel unfilmed)
        - Preface (in German), 1959 (Box 18, Reel unfilmed)
      - Meaning in the Visual Arts: Papers in and on Art History (Box 18, Reel unfilmed)
        - Preface, List of Illustrations and Captions, Footnotes, undated (Box 18, Reel unfilmed)
        - Chapter 3, "Abbot Suger and St.-Denis," circa 1944, (2 folders) (Box 18, Reel unfilmed)
        - Chapter 4, "Titian's Allegory of Prudence: A Postscript," undated (Box 18, Reel unfilmed)
        - Chapter 5, "The First Page of Giorgio Vasari's Libro, undated (Box 18, Reel unfilmed)
        - Chapter 6, "Albrecht Dürer and Classical Antiquity With an Excursas on the Illustrations of Apianus' Inscriptiones in Relation to Dürer," undated (Box 18, Reel unfilmed)
      - Problems in Titian, Mostly Iconographic (see also: Lecture Notes) (Box 18, Reel unfilmed)
        - Draft, undated (4 folders) (Box 18, Reel unfilmed)
        - Draft (List of Illustrations), undated (Box 18, Reel unfilmed)
        - Galley Proofs (corrected), undated, (2 folders) (Box 18, Reel unfilmed)
        - Manuscript, undated, (8 folders) (Box 18, Reel unfilmed)
        - Notes, undated (Box 18, Reel unfilmed)
      - Renaissance and Renascences in Western Art (Box 18, Reel unfilmed)
        - Footnotes and Illustrations (1960 edition), undated (Box 18, Reel unfilmed)
      - Saturn and Melancholy: Studies in the History of Natural Philosophy, Religion, and Art [with Raymon Klibansky and Fritz Saxl] (Box 18, Reel unfilmed)
        - Galley Proofs (corrected), 1936, (3 folders) (Box 18, Reel unfilmed)
    - Lectures (Box 19, Reel unfilmed)
      - Titian Lectures, New York University Institute of Fine Arts [published as Problems in Titian, Mostly Iconographic] (see also: Books) (Box 19, Reel unfilmed)
        - Drafts, undated, (3 folders) (Box 19, Reel unfilmed)
        - Draft ("Slide Desiderata"), undated (Box 19, Reel unfilmed)
        - Texts, 1963, (2 folders) (Box 19, Reel unfilmed)
- Biographical Information, 1905-1967, Series 3:; (Boxes 19-21; 0.5 linear ft.)
  This series is arranged by record type.
  - Awards and Certificates, 1950-1967, (see also: Box 20) (Box 19, Reel unfilmed)
  - Diplomas (honorary degrees), 1950-1962, (see also: Box 20 and OV 21) (Box 19, Reel unfilmed)
  - Membership Certificates, 1938-1963, undated, (see also: Box 20) (Box 19, Reel unfilmed)
  - Awards and Certificates, 1960-1967, (see also: Box 19) (Box 20 (sol), Reel unfilmed)
  - Cylindrical leather case for Rome University diploma (Box 20 (sol), Reel unfilmed)
  - Diplomas (doctorate; honorary degrees), 1905-1967, (see also: Box 19 and OV 21) (Box 20 (sol), Reel unfilmed)
  - Membership Certificates, 1943-1963, (see also: Box 19) (Box 20 (sol), Reel unfilmed)
  - Diplomas (honorary degrees), 1953-1962 (Box OV 21, Reel unfilmed)
- Printed Material, 1904-1990, undated, Series 4:; (Box 19; 0.5 linear ft.)
  - Articles About/Mentioning Panofsky, 1926-1962 (Box 19, Reel unfilmed)
  - Books, Bölsche, Wilhelm, Von Sonnen und Sonnenstäubchen, Kosmische Wanderungen; Weinstein, R., Die Philosophischen Grundlagen der Wissenschaften, 1904-1906 (Box 19, Reel unfilmed)
  - Certificates Presented to Abraham Flexner and Lessing J. Rosenwald (probably composed by Panofsky), 1951-1956 (Box 19, Reel unfilmed)
  - Clippings, 1941-1967, undated (Box 19, Reel unfilmed)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1967-1969 (Box 19, Reel unfilmed)
  - Lecture Announcement, Duke University, 1967 (Box 19, Reel unfilmed)
  - Membership List, The British Academy, 1957-1958 (Box 19, Reel unfilmed)
  - Memorial Program and Tributes, 1968-1969 (Box 19, Reel unfilmed)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Items Relating to Saturn and Melancholy, 1964-1990 (Box 19, Reel unfilmed)
  - Programs for Graduation Ceremonies (Panofsky awarded honorary degrees), 1947-1967 (Box 19, Reel unfilmed)
  - Obituaries (colleagues and friends), 1979-1987 (Box 19, Reel unfilmed)
  - Reviews of Panofsky's Writings (Box 19, Reel unfilmed)
    - Dürer (all editions), 1943-1959, undated (Box 19, Reel unfilmed)
    - Early Netherlandish Painting, 1954-1956 (Box 19, Reel unfilmed)
    - Gothic Architecture and Scholasticism, 1952-1958, undated (Box 19, Reel unfilmed)
    - The Iconography of Corregio's Camera di San Paolo, 1961-1963 (Box 19, Reel unfilmed)
    - "The Iconography of the Galerie François I at Fontainebleau" [with Dora Panofsky] (Gazette des Beaux Arts, 1958, pp. 113-190), 1959 (Box 19, Reel unfilmed)
    - Idea, 1952-1960, undated (Box 19, Reel unfilmed)
    - Meaning in the Visual Arts, 1955-1969 (Box 19, Reel unfilmed)
    - A Mythological Painting by Poussin, 1961 (Box 19, Reel unfilmed)
    - Pandora's Box [with Dora Panofsky], 1956-1958 (Box 19, Reel unfilmed)
    - Renaissance and Renasences, 1960-1969 (Box 19, Reel unfilmed)
    - Tomb Sculpture, 1964-1967, undated (Box 19, Reel unfilmed)